Hi, Preppies.
I hope you are ready to dive into today's lesson and learn something new.
Welcome to the IELTS Speaking intermediate course from PREP.
Alright, now let's explore the technique.
Compare past and present to expand answers for IELTS Speaking part 1.
First of all, let's review what we've learned in the previous lesson.
Do you still remember the formula for structuring your answers in IELTS Speaking part 1?
Yes, that is FER.
Using FER, we'll provide the answer along with additional information.
Typically, you would directly provide the answer for the answer part, right?
Today, I'll teach you the compare past and present method to expand the answer part.
As the name suggests, the compare past and present technique involves comparing
events or situations that occurred in the past and the present.
To be more specific, before directly addressing the current issue, we'll
mention the situation in the past to make a comparison.
So this method is only used when there is a contrast or
change between the information in the past and the present.
For example, to answer the question, do you like traveling?
Instead of just saying direct answer, yes, I'm into traveling, I'll mention
the changes in the travel preferences between the past and present to expand my answer.
Compare past and present answer.
In the past, I didn't enjoy traveling, as I thought it was
a waste of money, but nowadays I'm into it.
So you can expand the answer right from the answer part.
Additionally, the example sentence combines past and present tenses, which not
only increases the fluency and coherence score, but also helps to raise
grammatical range and accuracy score.
How to apply this technique to speaking part one.
We'll use this technique to compare the past with the present in the answer part.
Specifically, in each answer, we need to mention at least one point
from the past and one point from the present.
Then we'll continue to provide additional information using FER, Feeling - Example - Reason.
Please note that you should limit the length of the comparison points
and additional information to around two to three sentences.
Let's take a look at an example to better understand this technique.
In the answer part, we can see a comparison between the past and the present.
The second sentence serves as a reason.
The overall answer consists of two sentences.
Do you like traveling?
In the past, I didn't enjoy traveling, as I thought it was
a waste of money, but nowadays I'm very into it.
Two years ago, I took a summer camp trip to China, which
opened my eyes and made me realize the values that traveling can
offer me, such as personal growth, new knowledge, and meaningful connections.
From the example above, we can see that the comparison between the
past and the present in the answer is clearly expressed through two
contrasting phrases in the past and nowadays.
In addition to these phrases, I'll introduce some other expressions and phrases
for talking about the past and present.
Let's take a look and take careful notes, everyone.
So, what types of questions can this technique be applied to?
The technique Compare Past and Present can be used with various types
of questions, as long as they are about a specific object, phenomenon, trend, or habit.
Therefore, it can be applied to the following question types.
Liking and disliking questions.
For example, do you like eating out?
Basic description questions.
For example, tell me about your hometown.
Frequency questions.
For example, how often do you read books?
And trend questions.
For example, what kind of restaurants are popular in your country?
Great!
Now that we've covered the theoretical knowledge of the Compare Past and
Present technique, let's take a moment to review what you've learned via
some interactive questions before we move on to practice.
Well done guys!
Now let's try applying this technique to the following activity.
Your task is to expand the answer according to the requirements.
We have four questions.
For each question, you'll have 30 seconds to give your answer.
For example, we have the question, do you travel often?
Answer, compare plus feeling.
When I was small, but now that I am able to earn my own money, I feel.
So for this question, the requirement is to compare past and present.
Then expand the answer by talking about your feelings.
I'll provide a sample answer using the suggested structures that meet the given requirements.
Do you travel often?
Answer, compare plus feeling.
When I was small, I didn't have the opportunity to travel a lot, but now that I am able to earn my own money,
I can explore different places on my own much more frequently.
This enables me to gain more experiences and memories through my travels,
compared to before, which I feel incredibly grateful for.
Do you understand the requirements?
Please note that the length of the entire answer should be limited to two to three sentences only.
Let's start with the first question.
After each question, please read the sample answer and follow this technique for the remaining questions.
Are you ready? Let's go!
Do you like collecting things?
Answer, compare plus reason.
Actually, when I was in high school, now that I've grown older, as...
Answer, compare.
Actually, when I was in high school, I enjoyed collecting lipsticks and
earrings, so that I could show off to my friends and gain admiration from them.
Now that I've grown older, I no longer enjoy collecting things, since I don't seek attention from others anymore.
Number two.
Do you have a lot of friends?
Answer, compare plus reason plus feeling.
Not really.
In high school, however, that's no longer true for me because...
Answer, compare.
Not really.
In high school, I was popular and had a wide network of friends at school.
However, that's no longer true for me, because my circle has become
smaller and I just want to have a few close friends who I can share my interests with.
I also feel much happier now, since my current friends genuinely understand and support me.
What kind of clothes do you usually wear?
Answer, compare plus example.
Well, when I was younger, I used to wear.
But as I've grown older, for example...
Answer, compare.
Well, when I was younger, I used to wear more colorful and flashier clothes.
But as I've gotten older, my style has become more casual and minimalistic.
For example, I usually wear neutral colors and plain t-shirts that are easy to mix and match.
What is your favorite drink?
Answer, compare plus example.
Well, until last year, I...
But since then, I prefer...
Such as...
Answer, compare.
Well, until last year, I was addicted to caffeinated drinks such as
coffee and energy drinks, and they helped me to stay awake throughout the day.
But since then, I prefer healthier options that are good for my skin, such as fruit juice.
Good job everyone!
So now you have enough necessary vocabulary and technique to expand your
answers in IELTS Speaking Part 1.
To master these techniques, don't forget to practice regularly, and complete all the exercises preppies.
Now, let's call it a day.
See you guys in the next video.
Bye bye!